If I can break into the software
engineering world
without a computer science degree,
then so can you.
With so many computer
science or equivalents and job postings,
it seems discouraging.
But in today's video, I'm
going to be giving you a practical robot
that you can use to teach yourself
how to code with the intention
of getting you a job.
If you're new here, then Hi,
my name is Lewis and I'm on a mission
to inspire developers and tech enthusiasts
in the world of software engineering.
There's a ton of different roles
that you can pursue.
Front end, back end, Q way.
Like, there's so much.
So before we even touch this road map,
let's figure out what our end goal
should be.
If you love those crazy animated websites
or if you're into clean, sleek
and esthetic user interfaces,
it sounds like front end is for you.
No aid for design, no problem.
Choose back end.
If you really want
to get stuck under the hood.
And if you don't know, I have a video
describing what programing language
you should learn based off of the industry
that interests you the most.
So check that out if you want.
For the remainder of this video,
I'm just going to be referencing Fullstack
developer just because it kind of wraps
around everything.
However, this roadmap isn't
geared towards any specific industry.
Learn how to program.
So our first priority is how to program
as well as how to think like a programmer,
no matter what level
you are in your career,
you're always going to be learning
something new.
Software engineering requires a deep
understanding of how computers recode.
So start with a programing language
and do not, I repeat, do not spend
too much time thinking about what
programing language you should learn.
In my humble opinion, you should start
with JavaScript or Python.
And I have two reasons for this.
One, they're the most popular languages,
meaning it'll be much easier
to find resources
to help you become more fluent
and to concepts like variables, data
types.
Functions are already in these languages
and translates elsewhere.
Course Learn any programing language that
you want to learn like I'm not your boss.
Here are some resources
where you can learn programing for books.
No starch Press has some great options.
Specifically, look for the beginner books
that are targeted towards new programmers.
Bootcamps are going to be more pricey,
but the accountability is great
if you can fork out that cash
and if you're into video tutorials,
I recommend zero two Mastery,
which I've used before,
but is also the sponsor of today's video.
Listen, There's a ton of different videos
on YouTube, Udemy,
Twitter, whatever,
but none have the intentions
of helping you use these new skills
that you just developed.
Zero two Mastery is entire philosophy
revolves around outcome based results,
meaning that their courses
are designed to help you get hired
rather than just learn a skill
you can show at a party.
Sorry, are programmers getting invited
to parties asking for a friend?
You can take their free career path quiz
that will literally give you
a personalized career roadmap
based on your goals and experience,
which hopefully you did the step before
just fall on the courses, projects
and interview prep to land your dream job
and if you ever get stuck along the way,
which you know happens to the best of us,
the community of over 400,000 students
are here to help answer any questions.
Something I love as they've added,
I've dedicated a project section
where they've been launching a new project
you can build every week.
Nothing beats learning by doing.
And these projects are also a great way
to build up your portfolio and confidence.
So if you want to learn
the most in-demand skills, like literally,
I just saw a course go up
that was about large language
models and Zero
Mastery is an incredible resource
for new or existing developers like myself
who want to constantly stay ahead
to get started with their courses
and working towards
landing a job as a software
engineer, which, by the way,
can make up to $100,000 per year.
It'll only cost you
wait a minute, $23 a month.
How do these guys even make any money?
Graduate from zero
to mastery of land, a position at Tesla,
Amazon, Google and more.
Use the code in the description below
to level up your career
and support the channel.
30 days money back guaranteed.
Thanks again to Zero Mastery
for supporting the channel.
Once you've read a book or done
a course of some sort,
you'll have some familiarity
with how the programing language works.
Let's go to the next step.
Building a portfolio.
You're probably thinking
build a portfolio.
Like I have no idea what I'm doing.
Well, the good news, neither do I.
There are many reasons to start portfolio
really early.
One, it helps you build a community,
which, speaking of community,
I have a Discord channel
with over 9000 other developers.
I love to code so I would be happy
if you would join to help you
communicate abstract ideas in ways that
are understandable to a general audience.
And three, you can knock out a project
and create a portfolio in one go.
Now, if I were to start over,
this is how I was structure it.
I would create a web page that has a home
page, a blog page, and a project page.
This would mean that
I can have a little blurb about me.
I can start blogging to get my ideas
and learning out into the world.
Then a project page so I can showcase
all my amazing things that I've worked on.
If you want to build your own website,
you can use HTML, CSS and JavaScript.
You can also learn some advanced
frameworks like next JSA or Jungle.
But if you really just want something up
and fast,
then something like Ghost or WordPress
are two of my favorites.
This portfolio is going to act
like a diary moving forward.
We'll keep coming back to this
like as our home and continue to update it
so that in the future
we can prove that we have the experience
and that we know what we're talking about.
Build beginning projects.
You probably build some projects
and the courses
that you took, but water
things are coming off.
We're diving straight into the deep end,
whether you like it or not.
Sorry, that was weird.
Don't be alarmed
though is extremely common in software
engineering to go into something
without experience
and needing to understand
the requirements of how to get it done.
We have to set goals
because if you thought
you were learning during a course,
well then this.
While you're going to learn ten times
easier, you're three ways.
You are going to get a beginner
project idea.
One use Try to find some to think
of something easy you would like to use.
And three uses open source repository
to help you get started.
Now I love this repository right here,
but please use this carefully.
Each of these resources are linked
with pages on how you can build it,
which is going to take away
from your learning.
Just use the titles as ideas
and see what you think.
Here's how you're going to be successful
with this.
Let's grab
an idea using method one charge Djibouti.
I asked it for elicit beginner ideas.
All right.
I like this expense tracker.
An expense tracker. Interesting.
We would want to accept input.
Like the expense,
the category of it, and the price.
We can then maybe get a detailed output
after we are done inserting.
So I don't know about you,
but my stupid little pea brain right here
freezes under pressure,
so I would recommend
breaking this down into micro tasks.
Let me show you why not create input
for expense price and category to parse
input and lowercase
all values three store in a file type
so we can access it later for import
that file type and get all expenses
under a certain category and get the sum
and then five show the user the output.
Well,
I have seen like an overwhelming one app
is now being broken down
into five micro application.
Also, we just have some ideas for our blog
and portfolio.
Best way to ask for multiple
input in Python.
Best ways to store data
that is in a database.
Beautiful output in python. Guys.
I'm being serious here
communicating to an audience
really helps
you learn throughout your entire process.
And this diary approach that we're taking
is going to create a breadcrumb
for your whole entire programing journey,
which also means that people know
what you're talking about
and finding an idea
and breaking it down into a bunch of
small pieces is going to help you
code 20 times better.
And don't be scared to read documents.
Open next step.
Learn more advanced topics and databases.
Okay, You started building
some amazing beginner projects
and you kind of feel like a badass,
which is good for you.
I think you should feel like that.
So in my example that I mentioned
with the Fullstack developer,
while we can then go into more advanced
topics of Python
like Python has a web server, databases,
algorithms, again,
I have a more dedicated video to becoming
a full stack developer, front end
developer, a back end developer, whatever.
But here is the spark notes on this.
Software is often built
with many moving parts at the same time.
So let's start moving towards
that by building a back end web server
with Python.
Let's
think about how an application will work.
You have a smartphone, a microcomputer,
a website, whatever, talking to a server
in that server, some computation happens
and gathers memory from a database.
This architecture is simple,
but keep this in your head
when you think of developing apps.
If I wanted to learn Advanced Python,
for example, I would expand into SGI,
which would be Flask or Django Databases,
Sequel or NoSQL API development.
How can you get all the pieces of software
to talk to each other?
And if you haven't learned about classes
or object oriented,
then now is the time to do so.
Also, start looking into data structures
and algorithms.
Realistically,
at this point in your journey,
you definitely have stumbled
across them a little bit,
but they're an absolute essential
to computer science by even just
a glance of this will really help you
with your coding journey.
But stay tuned for that.
This is where it becomes
really important to have an end goal.
If you want to be a full stack developer,
then learn what I said above.
If you want to be in game
development, learn more advanced concepts
in your programing, language or engine.
The possibilities are endless.
But here are some general resources
that will work most of the time.
Most books on
no starch press have an advanced version
in most programing languages.
Zero to mastery
also have some advanced topics
you can use as well,
or join a coding community
and see what other people are working on
and what is required to make that
build and advanced at
your back.
In the scenario
now where you've learned a lot
but need to take off your water wings
while in this case
take your water wings off
and strap some bricks to your feet.
Sorry, was that too far?
At this rate, you've learned a lot.
You'll understand how technology works
together to create a harmonious app
and feel like you have the potential
to be as orchestrator.
I just made that up on the fly,
by the way.
We can do what we did before.
We can also find inspiration
and open source.
Again, I like this
project called Build Your Own Acts,
but beware, it gets pretty nuts.
Build an OS with rust like I want to go
outside once every three days at least.
Let's take the same idea you had
in the beginner project
and expand it with that new technology
you just learned.
Imagine of the expense tracker
that we made in the first half
had a web form that you could fill out
and then talked to a server with an API
and then had a database
that was able to store this information
as well as crunch
some numbers on the file.
The same philosophy applies when building
break it down with your dumb
little pea brain.
Well, sorry, I have the brain.
You're probably a little bit smarter than
I am, so create a form of three inputs.
Write a function that sends
an HTTP request with all the data,
Write a flash application
that accepts that information
and passes it.
Format
this to accept into an actual query,
write a query to get all existing inputs,
sign all together
serialize output, enter JSON
and send back to the user
and display the results in a fancy way.
Again,
this method allowed us to chop away at it
just one piece at a time,
but it also gives us some business
and communication tools as well.
By breaking down things into a scope
and how much you can execute it.
I am once again going to bother you
about the portfolio and blog
with this experience of building
this out comes a lot of great knowledge
that you can share best packages
to create forums, most secure
ways to insert you all JSON,
serializing for beginners, etc.
This content feedback and validation
you'll receive from this is what will help
you gather authority
to keep moving forward and connect
with other like minded developers.
Something we haven't even discussed yet
is working as a team.
Your blog and portfolio will help you
with this whole communication aspects,
but it is really important to learn tools
like get for example.
This will be key,
especially for the next step.
Getting an experience.
How can an entry level job require
experience
when I need that job to get experience?
I hate, hate, hate.
I hate to say this,
but it's the sad reality.
No education and no experience
is considered a risk to employers.
And realistically,
this shouldn't be true because graduates
could have just flown under the radar.
But that degree is serious authority.
Just a disclaimer.
This is what I did, and if you can please
avoid this as much as possible.
But I had to work for free to prove myself
as a young person.
I needed people to have a no rest attitude
when it came to hiring me,
so I would often do small jobs
or small businesses to help with this.
I'm very privileged to be in a situation
where I could work for free,
so please never aim to work for free gain.
Some real life experience
by consulting with small businesses
that often face software issues.
These can range from simple connectivity
between two software applications
to adding a small perform on a website
that can be printed out by offering
to solve a small problem for a client,
you can gain
valuable experience
working with real world requirements.
So let's say, for example,
they wanted to print in real time
when a web form submission happened again,
people in mentality, How can we do this?
Create a service in the middle
or on the server
that passes all of the data
once it is passed correctly,
send it to the computer in the office
and format on letterhead, paper, print
and save somewhere
that the job was a success.
Gluing two things together is arguably
some of the most effective way
that you can gain real world experience
with small businesses.
It's also small enough to the point
where you don't have to slave away
building an application
that someone asked you to do another way
you could get experience
is by contributing to open source.
Go to GitHub issues of any decent sized
project and it will be swarmed with bugs.
This could be a good opportunity
to work with code
in the real world and provide your input.
I will say that this method
is a little bit tougher just because
you have to be familiar with the project,
but it's still incredible nonetheless.
Computer Science related Topics.
Now all the advice I have led up to
this moment
have been extremely practical,
and that's on purpose.
But the word software
engineer is extremely controversial
and it's because of that one word
engineer.
Computer science is an extremely dense
topic that often involves
a lot of theory and abstract concepts.
However, it's extremely important
to have at least a surface level
understanding of computer science,
especially going into your interview
or even diving deep into your code.
For example.
How does that network work?
What responsibilities
does your operating system handle?
File systems, computer architectures,
maybe even cloud computing.
My recommendation
when it comes to learning computer
science is to start with roadmaps, stages,
self-learning, computer science charts,
and it provides a lot of resources
and lengths on each subject
that you click on.
Also, look into the open Source Society
University's computer science course.
In that course, some of the things overlap
with what we've already discussed,
so be a bit selective with it.
I'm a big fan of the calculus
and math courses specifically
for this reason, so make sure you take
that and catch up on math
interview, prep
your community involvement
and blog posts, show that you're skilled
at communicating what you know.
You have been doing that right?
So if you get overwhelmed in an interview,
well, we've already discovered
the method of breaking things
down the brain method.
That way you don't have to practice.
Okay, I'm joking. Of wake up.
Now is your time to practice
more theoretical programing problems
to show employers that you know
what you're talking about at this stage.
Hopefully you have some experience
which will let you explain to employers
how you're able to take requirements
and translate it over into the real world.
Technical interviews
may or may not be something that you have
to do depending on where you get a job,
but it's still worth taking time out
of your day to keep your brain on alert.
And I mean, let's be real here.
It's just good for your brain in general.
If this is the moment
you have to prove yourself,
you want to make the best impression
possible, It's really important
to not be discouraged in this moment.
You may struggle
in your first ten interviews.
Just keep going
and learn from your mistakes.
That's all you can do.
And you'll just ultimately
be a better person by the end of it.
Eventually, you'll get that reply back
saying that you got the job.
You're just some sample ways
on how you can prep less code.
This one is Mehmed everywhere online,
but there's a great collection
of resources to do technical interviews,
so use them at your disposal.
Mock interviews,
Get a friend to download an interview
and have them quiz you on the spot.
One of my favorites, the tech interview
handbook is an open source handbook
that will give you practical tips
on resume building algorithms and more.
An incredible resource.
So definitely check that one out.
Zero two Mastery
zero two Mastery has a course
where you can master the tech interview
specifically with large tech companies
like Google, Facebook, etc.
Congratulations.
It was a long journey, but your passion
and dedication did it for you.
Keep learning.
Great.
You landed the job.
Why are you still watching this video,
though?
A misconception I always had
when it came to working in the software
engineering industry was that eventually
I was going to get good
and that this whole learning process
will finally go away.
So if that's you and you're feeling
this way, come here for a sec.
That feeling never goes away.
Software engineering is a field
that is constantly throwing things at you
that you have never even seen before.
I mean, let's turn
this into a positive, though.
The feeling of constantly
having to learn and expand
or knowledge is ultimately
an extremely rewarding experience.
My biggest take away from this video
is that experience is the biggest leverage
that you can have when it comes to working
in the software engineering industry.
My roadmap is a very practical guide
on how you can get experience as fast
as possible. In computer science.
There's a ton of things
that you will need to learn,
but my roadmap is a very practical guide
on how you can get experience
as fast as possible so you can get a job.
I hope this roadmap was valuable to you
and helped
inspire you to either learn programing
or get into the industry.
If you want something a little bit
more laser focused and an industry.
Well, I have a full stack
developer roadmap or a back end
developer roadmap, so make sure you check
that out on my channel piece out Coders.