so I have some unfortunate news for
everyone um the days of learning HTML
CSS JavaScript and Landing a 100K a year
job within 6 months are sadly over but
to be honest I'm not sure they ever
existed in the first place however the
point is uh Landing a job as a self-
toop programmer is becoming exceedingly
more difficult than it has ever been in
the past the landscape of the tech
industry has significantly changed ever
since I got my first job uh back in
2016 matter of fact when I got my first
programming job back in
2016 I didn't have much experience and I
certainly didn't have like a killer
portfolio to show anybody um the extent
of my experience included some classes
that I had taken in high school and some
really crappy Java applications that I
had written but somehow someway I still
managed to land a part-time coding job
with relatively no effort now granted I
did land this job through a string of
connections I made which kind of just
goes to show how powerful networking can
be but still if I were trying to get a
job in this market with the amount of
experience I had back in 2016 I would
probably have a better chance at winning
the lottery because the reality is the
market is just terrible right now I had
someone recently reach out to me who had
just finished their computer science
degree they had uh done an internship at
meta but they were significantly
struggling to just get call backs from
recruiters so if people with degrees and
with experience working at Big tech
companies are struggling you can only
imagine how hard it is for those people
who were told by influencers like me
that it's possible to get a job in
programming without a college degree and
to be clear I'm not trying to scare you
if if you are self-taught you can still
break into the industry but it's
important that we acknowledge that the
industry is in a pretty rough spot right
now layoffs are happening left and right
and a lot of developers are struggling
to find jobs and while I do believe that
the market will get better I'm not
entirely convinced that it will ever
return to its previous levels which is
why I say you will have to work
significantly harder than what you would
have done in the past to compete with
all the other competition out there and
when I say all the other competition I
don't have any statistics to back the
idea that the market is
oversaturated but it does feel a bit
oversaturated okay I mean with all the
coding boot camps turning out grads
every 10 months and all the influencers
promoting learning how to code and with
all the hype around computer science
over the past few years it feels like
the supply of developers has gone way up
meaning that if you want to break into
the industry you will have to do things
to really stand out from everyone else
so what do I mean by this well simply
put you're going to have to have the
type of experience that employers are
looking for from the get-go so I want to
walk through an example with you let's
take a look at the average entrylevel
developer job posting so this is for a
full stack entry-level react developer
position
and these qualifications are generated
from Google because they're stripped
directly from the original job posting
now right off the bat the first thing
you may notice about this entry-level
posting is that they want two years of
experience which mind you is something
that isn't an atypical ask for entry
level positions nowadays and with proper
laying out of your resume you can look
like you have 2 years of experience even
if you spent those two years learning
this is something that we'll go over in
a minute other than that you will see
that you need experience with JavaScript
react Redux HTML CSS rest apis
authentication mechanisms knowing how to
optimize react projects continuous
integration Technologies and agile and
scrum knowledge and then the very last
Point here a computer science degree now
I don't want this to scare you too much
because if you display a high level of
Competency in the above points this can
be overlooked in some instances but the
reality is that if you're competing with
somebody who is equally as good as you
and they have a computer science degree
they're going to get the job which is
why I said in the beginning of this
video you're going to have to do things
that really stand out from all the other
competition so if you really want to
stand out you can look at this job
posting or other job postings like this
one as sort of the recipe for you
getting into the industry now you will
likely never work for this company but
the idea is that we can find job
postings for jobs that we're interested
in and use them as a template for the
type of project we can build that will
help us get another job later down the
road so you can take this text stack and
the processes laid out in this posting
and use this text stack and the
processes to create full stack real
world use case applications okay to
really stand out as a self-taught
developer today it is pivotal that you
display a high level of Competency in
the way that real companies develop real
software so that when you start
interviewing for a company you will look
like the type of candidate that will hit
the ground running and how do you gain
experience into building real world
software as a self-taught developer with
no job experience well you do that by
building real world full stack
applications most product or service
driven companies prioritize the
development and maintenance of full
stack crud applications which is why it
is an extremely safe bet to build these
types of projects by building these
types of projects from the ground up you
will gain a large depth of programming
experience which you can use to create a
beefed up resume so let's run through an
example let's say this is the type of
job I'm going for the one that lists out
all these qualifications the very first
step is to come up with a project idea
and because this is for the sake of
learning this project idea absolutely
does not have to be unique okay so pick
a hobby like reading you can build a
very robust CR app around the idea of
book reviewing book rating sharing books
with friends so on and so forth matter
of fact this idea already exist exist
it's a platform known as Goodreads you
can take good reads build it from the
ground up with a slightly uh tweaked
feature set and then Rebrand it as your
own so for this example let's say we
have our project idea building a good
reads type of application let's go
through how we can gain experience in
the other qualifications listed out in
this posting so first off we'll build
our front end using react typescript and
the Redux Library so we can check off
the these bullet points here and by
using react we'll naturally gain
experience into HTML with jsx which is
similar enough and then we'll also gain
experience into CSS we can gain
JavaScript experience by deploying an
API of some sorts using an AWS service
let's say such as AWS Lambda and because
we'll need some sort of database for our
API to fetch and save data records we'll
create a database maybe something like
mongod DB and and again host it with
Amazon we can Implement some login page
in the app that uses the type of Json
authentication that this job posting
mentions and as for agile and scrum we
can spend a few hours doing some
research into how companies follow scrum
practices and then follow those
practices while creating our portfolio
project matter of fact learning these
agile and scrum practices should be done
before you dive into the creation of
your portfolio project as they are
essentially project management
techniques that can significantly help
you with the overall development of your
project while at the same time giving
you Real World Experience into how
companies use agile to develop their
software and finally we can use
something like GitHub actions to
automatically deploy our release builds
giving us some highlevel exposure to how
cic CD works so in theory we could build
and deploy this application using the
practices I've just mentioned and extend
that over a 6 to 12 month time frame of
coding deploying coding deploying and if
you worked on a full stack application
of this sorts following this plan I've
just laid out for again 6 to 12 months
by adding new features refining existing
features fixing bugs and actually
deploying it to the public Not only
would you gain the type of experience
that real companies value you would have
killer points to mention on your resume
you would have projects that not even
the average computer science student has
on their resume because the thing is
most people list very basic projects on
their resume that they developed within
one to two weeks so as for the resume
here is how you could create an
entry-level developer rume with the
project idea that I've just gone over
now this is a fake resume it's not real
and it should just serve as as an
example or as a model for the type of
resume that you could create so if
you're interested in downloading this
rume head to the link in the description
to sign up for my newsletter and upon
signing up for my newsletter you'll gain
access to download this resume for free
you also gain access to my free ebook 02
full-time programmer in five steps
anyways that is the highlevel overview
of the type of work that you will need
to do to land a job in this market as a
self-d do programmer and even if you're
not a self toop programmer you could
greatly benefit from building these
types of projects anyways thank you for
making it this far in the video and I
will catch you in the next one